Guide to the Albert Lyonel Harris Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.049
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Albert Lyonel Harris Photographs
1937-1957, (Bulk 1937-1938)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harris, Albert Lyonel, 1907-
ALBA.PHOTO.049
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Albert Lyonel "Abe" Harris (1907-c.1973?) was a volunteer with the 4th Artillery Group of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He was also associated with the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) and a representative of the Junior Section of the International Workers Order during the Spanish Civil War, making recommendations on problems of child welfare in war-torn Spain. Harris saw action at Fuentes de Ebro, Teruel, Cuenca and Levante. The images in this collection were acquired by Harris in the course of his service as an artilleryman and social worker/observer in Spain. The collection contains combat and non-combat photographs of artillery, bombed/shelled cities, injured soldiers, military vehicles (aircraft and armored personnel carriers), Spanish Civilians (men, women and children), and snapshots of Spanish cities and towns.
Provenance
The Albert Harris Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Harris's widow in 1974. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Harris Photograph Collection were separated from the Harris manuscript material at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Albert ("Abe") Harris (1907-c.1973?) was born in Chicago, Illinois and educated at the University of Manitoba, the University of Chicago, and the New School for Social Research. From 1924-1934 he worked as a social worker and as a researcher at New York University. During the Spanish Civil War he was a volunteer with the 4th Artillery Group of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He was also associated with the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) and a representative of the Junior Section of the International Workers Order, charged with the task of assessing the situation of orphaned and destitute children in Spain, and making recommendations as to aid. The International Workers Order (IWO) was a Communist-affiliated insurance and fraternal order founded in 1930. Harris saw action at Fuentes de Ebro, Teruel, Cuenca and Levante, and also toured hospitals and civilian areas, observing conditions and presumably reporting back to the U.S. organizations to which he was connected.
In his later life Harris pursued his interest in social work in venues that reflected his traditional Jewish upbringing. He worked in the 1940s and 1950s for the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society (HIAS), the Jewish Settlement of the Lower East Side, N.Y., the National Refugee Service and other Jewish organizations.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Photographs. The collection contains combat and non-combat photographs of artillery, bombed/shelled cities, injured soldiers, military vehicles (aircraft and armored personnel carriers), snapshots of the daily life of Spanish civilians (men, women and children) and Spanish cities and towns. There is one image of Polish volunteers attributed to Film Polski, Warsaw and one image of the International Brigade Anniversary attributed to Syd Harris. Apart from these two images, there is no indication of the origin of the photographs in the collection. Over 80% of the images are quite small (1 1/8 x 5/8 to 1 1/8 x 1 1/8 inches). Except where indicated, all the photographs were taken in Spain.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 49:1:1:1.
Folders are arranged in one series:
Missing Title
I: Photographs.
Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Children.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Harris, Albert Lyonel, 1907-
- Series I: Photographs
  - Art: Sculpture, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artillery, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - At the Front: Combat, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, General, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Bicycle Troops, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Marching, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Officer Addressing Troops, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, On the Train, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Troops At Attention, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bombed/Shelled Buildings, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Demonstrations/Rallies: In Spain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fortifications, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Garland, Walter and [?], ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Goyen, Emil and Jackson, [?]: Brunete, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Groups: Unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Harris, Albert, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Harris, Albert: Harris Family at Home in New York, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Harris, Albert: International Brigade Anniversary [in U.S.?], 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Individual Portraits: Unidentified [Includes Fred Lutz?], ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Injured Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Brigade Anniversary: Dining Hall with Anti-Fascist Posters [in U.S.?], 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Military Vehicles: Aircraft, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Military Vehicles: Armored Personnel Carrier and Crew, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Polish Volunteers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Propaganda: Posters, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Shipboard: United States, New York City ( SS Normandie), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Spanish Cities, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Spanish Civilians: General, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Spanish Civilians: Children, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Spanish Civilians: Men, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Spanish Civilians: Women, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Spanish Countryside, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Spanish Countryside: Beach Scenes, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Spanish Militiawomen: Maria [?], Angelina [?], Teresa [?], Murcia, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Spanish Sailors, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Spanish Villages, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Spanish Villages: Animals, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Spanish Workers: Laundrywomen, ca.1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 40)